Contact

ahmed.musawir@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/ ahmedmusawir (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

REST APIs

strapi

sanity

Languages

Bengali

Hindi

English

Urdu

Certifications

CompTIA A+

Network+

Sun Certified Systems Administrator

Security+

MCP + I

Ahmed Musawir

Sr. Web Developer & React/Next.js FullStack Engineer Alpharetta, Georgia, United States

Summary

An IT professional with 16 years of solid experience in the U.S. IT industry and 6 years as a freelance Web Developer, working the last 6 years as a React/Next.js Engineer looking for a position in a dynamic environment with opportunities for further learning and growth.

PORTFOLIO:

https://themoose.cyberizestaging.com/

YOUTUBE CHANNEL:

https://www.youtube.com/@htmlfivedev

TECHNOLOGIES:

HTML5, CSS, SCSS, TypeScript, Javascript (ES6, OOP), jQuery, React.js, Next.js, Firebase 9, Node.js, Express, PHP, SQL, MySQL, Firestore, Unix Korn Shell, BASH shell, SSH, REST APIs, GraphQL Etc.

TOOLS:

Docker, Strapi, Sanity.io, Material UI, Bootstrap 5x, React Bootstrap, Styled Component, Tailwind, Git & Github, Compass, Composer, Wordmove, NPM, MAMP Pro, Photoshop, Vi, Vim, Nano, VSCode, Atom, Gulp.js, Docker, Virtual Box, VMWare, Mac OSX, Windows 10, CentOS 7, WordPress, Woocommerce, ACF Pro, SMB2, PHPMyAdmin, etc.

HOSTING:

VPS Management, Plesk, Cpanel, WHM, Digital Ocean Dropletbased hosting w/ shell script automation, Docker-based deployments via shell script, DNS management, Next.js and Strapi hosting with SSL via Nginx reverse lookup, shell script-based React App deployment, shell script-based Next.js App deployment & update via Github, Vercel, Netlify, etc.

Experience

Cyberize Group

Sr. Web Developer & React/Next.js Engineer January 2019 - Present (4 years 9 months)

Florida, United States

- -- Developed Apps w/ ES6/React.js & Next.js & w/ backend API-s & CMS-s (Strapi, Sanity.io, GraphCMS, WordPress, WooCommerce, etc.)
- -- Developed WordPress Websites & Plugins from Scratch w/ ES6 JS, React.js & PHP
- -- Deployed React/Next.js-based applications via KSH shell scripts, Docker, SSH & Docker Hub
- -- Managed & Maintained 3 Linux- based VPS-s with WHM, cPanel/Plesk & Docker (Development, Staging & Production)

DeepCast.ai

Frontend React Developer

November 2017 - December 2018 (1 year 2 months)

Texas, United States

- Did research and collected information for the CTO about React-related tech stacks (Next.js, React Starter kits, etc.), better responsive frameworks/UI/Ux platforms (Bootstrap, React Bootstrap, Ant Design, Material, etc.), JS backends (Node.js, Express) and React-based application deployment frameworks like Docker, Zeit, etc.
- Developed company website as a React App according to design
- Used Styled Component, Bootstrap, React Bootstrap and Flexbox for styling and mobile responsive work
- Pulled data into the site by setting up a dummy backend using the JSON Server hosted with Docker
- Converted that React App into a website & a progressive web app with Next.js
- After building the site published into staging (Digital Ocean droplet) using KSH shell script, Docker & Docker Hub
- Deployed site into production (Zeit hosting platform)

HTMLfiveDev.com

Freelance Web Designer and Developer

November 2012 - October 2017 (5 years)

Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia

Worked for Omen Interactive (Sarasota, Florida) from Apr 2016 - May 2018. http://omeninteractive.com/

Currently available on Upwork.com & Freelancer.com

FULLY CUSTOM WORDPRESS SITE BUILDS:

- PSD to WordPress conversion
- Custom Site from scratch based on my own Theme Development Framework called Moose Framework 2.0
- This Framework follows all the best practices and methods suggested by WordPress.org and more
- The framework is built from the ground up with WP Security & Page Load Speed in mind
- Analytics tracking is a built-in feature
- The SCSS version of Bootstrap 4 is used so that all its Variables can be customized
- Gulp.js is integrated into the theme to minify & unify all Javascripts & SCSS

THEME CUSTOMIZATION (3rd Party):

- Customize pretty much any Premium Theme in the market
- I wire the child theme with an SCSS compiler and Bourbon/Compass mixin Libs
- Also, use WP-SCSS plugin to compile SCSS in the production environment

WORDPRESS BACKEND CUSTOMIZATION (without any plugin):

- WP Admin screen/dashboard, WP Admin menus, Post/Page Editors, and Sidebars etc.
- Add Custom Meta boxes, Linked Images, Videos etc.
- Add Custom Post Types & Custom Taxonomies
- Use Custom Post data anywhere with Custom WP_Query loops

FAST & SECURE DEPLOYMENT:

- Setup SSH (Secure Shell) connection between Staging and Local Dev box.
- Then set up a push/pull relationship between them
- Deploy/update Staging sites in seconds securely via ssh from local dev system

WORDPRESS PLUGINS & WIDGET:

- Build plugins and widgets using WP Settings API, WP Options API, WP Rest API, WP Widgets API ...
- Have proficiency in the WP REST API data manipulation (read, write, update & delete)
- Can extend the REST API with PHP
- Can build Custom Endpoints into the REST API

eTechCorners.com

Web Master

September 2010 - October 2012 (2 years 2 months)

Macon, Georgia Area

WORDPRESS SECURITY:

Lockdown WP Security manually via PHP code

Build custom login page and signup page

Lockdown dir browsing via server configuration

Lockdown wp-config.php file access with .htaccess

Configure firewall and malware scanning via WordFence Plugin

Lockdown WP DB with password hardening and DB prefix update

Usually, train my clients on how to manage longer and harder passwords with LastPass

WORDPRESS PAGE LOAD SPEED:

Install and configure Server-based caching

Write custom Browser caching code on .htaccess

Perform my own Speed Benchmark Tests (With Gtmetrix & Pingdom)

Manually optimize images with Photoshop

Implement CDN to enhance speed and security overall.

WEB HOSTING:

WHM & Cpanel

Create accounts

Setup DNS

Setup MX record

Setup SSL(https) and SSH

Add or delete Addon Domains

Handle 301, 302 and wildcard redirects

VPS (Virtual Private Server) Management:

Configure and manage a VPS running CentOS (Linux)

Install & configure LAMP stack (Linux, Apache, MySQL & PHP) from scratch

Write BASH Shell scripts to automate backend tasks

Automate updating WP Core, Themes and Plugins via wp-cli, bash script and cron jobs

Automate backing up and restoring WP data with shell scripts and wp-cli Upload backups to remote Google Drives from Linux hosts

ECOMMERCE:

Woocommerce:

Install and configure the plugin

Perform all basic store functions

Create Custom themes for Woocommerce

Customize any Woocommerce Theme

Setup events and triggers via Google Tag Manager

Shopify:

Set up an online store

Perform all basic Shopify tasks

Pull Shopify products into WordPress

Setup a Wordpress Blog with Shopify Store

Implement shopify products on Flat HTML based sites

Write custom BuyButton.js code without iFrame and thus making it trackable Setup Google Analytics & FaceBook Ecommerce events tracking on a Store Less Shopify account (a \$9/month account)

AT&T

Sr. Systems Analyst

February 2002 - July 2010 (8 years 6 months)

Provided 4th tier support for 15 multi-tier web-based applications (Retail and Financial) consisting of Java, Weblogic, iPlanet, Oracle and Sun Solaris.

Designed, developed, implemented and supported a Web based application management and monitoring system called 'Zion' using Perl, Korn shell, Telnet, RSH, XML and Oracle SQL. Also, automated nightly backup of that

App onto remote file servers and update of mirror sites as a failover measure. The App was hosted with Apache Web Server on Solaris.

Automated 'Morning Checkout' process of Apps, which verified and validated pre-production hour system status utilizing Korn shell, Bash shell, rsh, Perl, and mailx.

Automated daily and weekly database indexing job along with old index file and other billing data backup and daemon bouncing for payment processing application 'Quickpay Atlanta' and 'Quickpay Dallas'. Also, automated the failover mechanism between Atlanta and Dallas.

Responded to numerous 'Telalert' pages from various systems company wide and researched troubleshot and resolved production issues accordingly.

Initiated and joined numerous conference bridges during production emergences to troubleshoot and resolve issues along with the Network team, Development team, Production DBA team, Firewall team, and Enterprise Support team.

Created virtual environments using VMware, Deployed and configured applications to re-created production issues.

Designed, developed, implemented, and supported 'Osiris', an on-demand Web-based application management and monitoring tool using LAMP (Linux, Apache, MySQL, and PHP), Korn Shell, XML, and Java. The Apps functionalities included displaying system status of numerous remote Sun Servers and applications, system disk cleanup over the web, remote invocation of shell scripts to perform various tasks, making Java calls to live Weblogic servers to collect status info etc. All requests were made over encrypted secure connection using SSH.

Red Celsius Inc.

Quality Assurance Analyst July 2001 - January 2002 (7 months)

- # Wrote Test Plans and Test Cases in Test Director and executed them.
- # Performed manual tests and generated bug reports.
- # Automated regression tests via WinRunner 7i.
- # Deployed application on Weblogic 6 on Solaris 8.
- # Setup Lab environments with VMware and deployed application for testing.

Automated system clean up process in preparation for new build deployment with Korn Shell and mailx.

Solutions inc.

IT Trainer

July 2000 - June 2001 (1 year)

Provided comprehensive training on computer hardware and networking, UNIX shell scripting, ASP and Java scripting, Oracle PL/SQL programming and WinRunner automation.

Administered and upgraded the network from Windows NT to Windows 2000 based network.

Configured DNS, DHCP, SQL Server, Proxy Server, and Test Director 7 on IIS.

Configured Apache Web server and local router firewall to host company Website.

Administered users and groups on Solaris and Linux for the Labs.

Installed and configured Java SDK and Jakarta Tomcat on Windows NT, Solaris, and Linux.

BellSouth Mobility D C S

Systems Analyst

July 1998 - June 2000 (2 years)

- # Provided second level support for 'StoreMaster' application for all Bellsouth retail stores.
- # Provided remote administration for Windows NT 4.0 based network via RAS (Remote Access Services).
- # Ran SQL queries on Sybase database to collect data or perform updates to resolve production issues.
- # Researched, verified, and manually processed failed credit card transactions from Database.
- # Picked up trouble tickets from call log, called customer back, troubleshot and resolved issues.
- # Provided training to team members on new application, management and support policies.

HP

Systems Engineer
January 1997 - June 1998 (1 year 6 months)

Savannah, Georgia Area

Provided phone (hardware and OS) support to all the Digital/Compaq Desktops, Laptops, Network Cards, Digital Alpha Servers, and Compaq Proliant Servers on Windows, UNIX, and Linux Platform.

Logged every call with detailed description after troubleshooting. Walked customers through installation of necessary software and drivers, dispatched field techs if necessary with proper parts to replace.

Recreated and resolved hardware and OS issues in Lab environment along with senior engineers.

Education

San Francisco International University

Master of Business Administration (MBA), Information Technology Project

Management · (2004 - 2006)

San Francisco International University
Bachelor of Commerce (B.Com.), Computer Information
Systems · (2001 - 2004)